We all want to eat
the kinds of foods
that make us feel
better and live longer.
But there’s so much conflicting
information out there,
so many nutrition opinions.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s my job to give you
the information you need
to make the healthiest
choices possible.
Today, we look at some of the best
research on plant based meat.
And we start with
the SWAP-MEAT study
that put Beyond Meat
products to the test.
As the chair of Harvard’s
Nutrition department put it,
transitioning global diets
towards healthy plant-based
dietary patterns would require
large-scale public health efforts
but could be instrumental
in ensuring future human health.
In my book How Not to Diet,
in the chapter on habit formation,
I talk about how you can change
your existing bad habits to good ones,
or establish new good
habits from scratch,
using a technique known
as implementation intentions.
Instead of vague self-promises
to “do our best,”
implementation intentions
are specific if-then plans
to perform a particular
behavior in a specific context.
They take the form
of When situation X arises,
I will perform response Y.
For example, If I get hungry
after dinner, I will eat an apple.
If the triggering circumstance
is a regular, daily occurrence,
implementation intentions can be
the beginning of a beautiful habit.
So, what about using Implementation
Intentions to cut down on meat?
After all, most food choices
are just due to ingrained habits,
and meat is no exception.
Here, they were
trying to get people
to change from
a climate perspective,
noting more greenhouse gas
emissions from animal ag
than all cars, trucks, trains,
ships, and planes combined,
but whatever the reason,
researchers randomized people
to form “if–then plans”
(for example, “If I visit
the university cafeteria
for lunch tomorrow,
then I will choose one
of the vegetarian meals”).
Motivating people to consciously
form an implementation intention
specifically how to implement a goal
seems to be such a simple technique,
but it works.
Forming an implementation
intention led people
not only to think more
often about their intention
to reduce meat consumption
but also to eat less meat
despite the strong
force of habit.
On one hand, breaking
a habit may be
one of the most challenging
tasks we set ourselves.
On the other hand,
a first yet effective step
in getting there seems to be
writing down the goal of change
in the form of an if-then
statement on a piece of paper.
Even a journey of a thousand
miles begins with a single step.
How else can we transition
to reduced-meat diets?
We talked about making the healthier
option the default option.
We could also minimize disruption,
by producing affordable,
recognizable, and tasty
plant-based meat alternatives.
The topic of plant-based
meat alternatives
has been discussed
for several decades,
but it has only recently become
one of the hottest topics
in the food
and research communities.
After all, one of the largest
perceived barriers
for switching diets was the
enjoyment of eating meat, and so,
if you can deliver a similar
taste and mouthfeel,
it could help people shift.
And it seems
like it’s working.
In recent years in North America,
plant-meat sales grew by 37 percent.
The company that makes
the Beyond Burger
decided to put up
or shut up
by funding a study
through Chris Gardner’s
prestigious lab at Stanford.
A randomized crossover
trial to compare the effect
of consuming plant-based
alternative meat to animal meat
on human health by having people
eat at least 2 servings a day
of Plant versus Animal
meat for 8 weeks each,
while keeping everything
else as similar as possible.
So, instead of burgers and beef
from cows, sausage from pigs,
and breasts from chickens,
they ate burgers, sausage,
and chicken made from plants.
Now, if they were trying to game
it to give Beyond Meat an advantage,
they’d have chosen the worst
possible meats to compare it to,
but no, the meats
were organic, grass-fed
to give the fairest
comparison possible.
So, what happened? Significant
drop in TMAO levels
during the plant-
based meat phase.
That’s a good thing,
as I’ve explored before.
The consumption of meat dairy
and eggs can be turned
by bad gut bacteria
into trimethylamine,
which is oxidized by
our liver into TMAO,
which is associated with
heart failure, kidney failure,
and our number one killer,
atherosclerosis,
the hardening of our arteries.
The plant-based meat
group also achieved
a significant drop in cholesterol.
No surprise, given the lower
saturated fat intake.
Of course, if they had been
eating whole plant foods instead,
like beans, saturated fat
would have been way down,
fiber way up,
and sodium way down.
In fact, there was basically
no difference in sodium intake;
so, no surprise,
no difference in blood pressure.
The big surprise was weight.
During the plant-
based meat phase,
they inadvertently
lost a couple pounds.
Some of the plant-based
meats are highly processed,
and normally you’d expect
people to gain weight;
however, weight was modestly but
statistically significantly lower
after 8 weeks on the Plant
rather than on the Animal phase.
Notably, this was observed
despite no differences
in reported total
calorie intake
or physical activity
levels between each phase.
Same calories,
yet less weight.
We’ve seen this before.
Same calorie restriction,
yet more weight-loss
eating more plant-based,
slimmer waist, less body fat.
This may be from the fewer
branched-chain amino acids
in plant protein
compared to animal protein
or because the resting metabolic
rate in those eating vegetarian
is as much as
20 percent higher;
so, you’re basically just burning
more calories in your sleep.
Finally today,
we look at the different impacts
of plant vs animal protein.
So, are these plant-based
burgers healthy or not?
And the answer is…
compared to what?
Eating is kind of a zero-sum game;
every food has an opportunity cost.
I mean, every time we
put something in our mouth
it’s a lost opportunity to put
something even healthier in our mouth.
So, if you want to know
if something is healthy,
you have to compare it to
what you’d be eating instead.
So, for example,
are eggs healthy?
Compared to a breakfast
link sausage? Yes!
But compared to oatmeal?
Not even close.
But look, sausage is considered
a group 1 carcinogen.
In other words, we know consumption
of processed meat causes cancer.
Each 50-gram serving a day,
that’s a single breakfast link,
was linked to an 18% higher
risk of colorectal cancer.
So, the risk of getting colorectal
cancer eating one link a day
is about the same as the increased
risk of lung cancer you’d get
breathing secondhand smoke all
day living with a smoking spouse.
So, compared to sausage,
eggs are healthy,
but compared to oatmeal,
eggs are not.
So, when it comes to Beyond Meat
and Impossible Burger,
yeah, they may be better in
that they have less saturated fat,
but, hey, you want
less saturated fat?
Plant-based meat
alternatives are no match
for unprocessed plant foods,
such as beans or lentils.
And a bean burrito or lentil
soup could certainly fill
the same culinary niche
as a lunchtime burger.
But if you are going to
have some kind of burger,
it’s easy to argue that the
plant-based versions are healthier.
There is a sodium issue, and
it’s not that much, if any, lower,
in saturated fat, since
they use coconut oil,
which is basically just
as bad as animal fat;
there’s not much
advantage on that front.
Though the total protein is
similar across the board,
does this matter? Or Is there any
advantage to eating plant protein
over animal protein?
Let’s look at the association
between animal and plant
protein intake and mortality.
In the twin Harvard cohorts,
following more than 100,000 men
and women over decades, “…after
adjusting for other dietary
and lifestyle factors, animal
protein intake was associated
with a higher risk [of] mortality,
particularly [dying from
cardiovascular disease], whereas
higher plant protein intake
was associated with
a] lower all-cause mortality”,
meaning a lower risk of dying
from all causes put together.
So, “replacing animal protein
of various origins
with plant protein was associated
with lower mortality”,
especially if you’re replacing
processed meat and egg protein,
which were the worst. But when
it comes to living a longer life,
plant protein sources beat out
each and every animal protein source.
Not just better
than bacon and eggs,
but better than burgers, chicken,
turkey, fish, and dairy protein.
Together with other studies, these
“findings support the importance
of protein sources for the
long-term health outcome
and suggest plants constitute
a preferred protein source
compared [to] animal foods.” Why?
Well, unlike animal protein, plant
protein has not been associated
with increased levels
of the cancer-promoting
growth hormone IGF-1, for example.
Now, soy protein is similar
enough to animal protein
that at high enough doses, like eating
two Impossible Burgers a day,
you may bump your IGF-1.
But the only reason we care
about IGF-1 is cancer risk,
and if anything, higher soy
intake is associated with
a decreased risk of cancer.
For example, a recent systematic
review and meta-analysis found
that soy protein intake was
associated with a decreased risk
in breast cancer mortality;
we’re talking “a 12 percent reduction
in breast cancer death
[associated with] each 5-gram-a-day
increase in soy protein intake.”
But the high soy groups
in these studies
were on the order of
more than 16 grams a day,
associated with a
whopping 62% lower risk
of dying from breast cancer.
More than 10 grams of soy
protein a day may be good,
associated with cutting
breast cancer mortality risk
nearly in half, and getting
more than 16 grams a day
may be better, which is like
one Impossible Burger a day.
But we simply don’t
know what happens
at consumption levels
far above that.
Plant protein has also been
linked to lower blood pressure,
reduced LDL cholesterol, and
improved insulin sensitivity.
No wonder “substitution of
plant protein for animal protein
has been related to a lower incidence
of cardiovascular disease
and type 2 diabetes.”
Indeed, 21 different studies following
nearly a half million people,
and “high… animal protein
intakes [were] associated with
an increased risk of [type 2 diabetes],
whereas [even just] moderate
plant protein intake
is associated with a decreased
risk of [type 2 diabetes].”
OK, but these were just
observational studies.
They all tried to control for other
dietary and lifestyle factors,
but you can’t prove cause-and-effect,
until...you put it to the test.
The “Effect of Replacing Animal
Protein with Plant Protein
on [blood sugar] Control in
Diabetes: A Systematic Review
and Meta-Analysis of
Randomized Controlled Trials.”
Even just switching out about
a third of your protein
from animal to plant sources
yielded significant improvements
in long-term blood sugar control,
and fasting blood sugars, and insulin.
You can do the same thing
looking at cholesterol.
Here’s a systematic review and
meta-analysis of randomized
controlled trials on the effect
of plant protein on blood fats.
And indeed, swapping in plant
protein for animal protein
decreases LDL cholesterol,
and this benefit occurs
whether you start out at high
cholesterol or low cholesterol,
whether you’re swapping out
dairy, or meat, and eggs,
and whether you’re swapping in
soy or other plant proteins.
We’ve known about the beneficial
effects of soy on cholesterol
going back nearly 40 years, but
other sources of plant protein
can do it as well. Yeah, but
we’re not swapping beans for beef.
These products are mostly
just isolated plant proteins,
mostly pea protein isolate
in the case of Beyond,
and concentrated soy protein
in the case of Impossible.
If you just isolate out
the plant proteins themselves
are you still going to get benefits?
Yes, surprisingly. Check it out.
Interestingly, the researchers
concluded, that they did not ﬁnd
a signiﬁcant difference between
protein isolate products
and whole food sources, “suggesting
that the cholesterol-lowering
effects are at least,
in part, attributable
to the plant protein
itself rather than just
the associated nutrients.”
So, it’s not just because
plant protein travels
with fiber or less saturated fat.
Plant proteins break down
into a different distribution
of amino acids; and so, it’s
like if you give people arginine,
an amino acid found
more in plant foods,
that alone can bring
down people’s cholesterol.
And even plant protein concentrates
used in these products
aren’t pure protein, retaining
a few active compounds
such as phytosterols and antioxidants,
which also can have beneficial effects.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.